Finding Aid for the Morton I. Grossman Papers Biomed.0451
UCLA Library Special Collections
Morton I. Grossman papers
1947-1985
UCLA Library Special Collections
Grossman, Morton I.
Biomed.0451
0.4 linear feet (1 box)
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Prof. Morton I. Grossman, 2007.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9976967513606533
We are committed to providing ethical, inclusive, and anti-racist description of the materials we steward, and to remediating existing description of our materials that contains language that may be offensive or cause harm. We invite you to submit feedback about how our collections are described, and how they could be described more accurately, by filling out the form located on our website: Report Problematic Content and Description in UCLA's library collections and archives.
Administrative/Biographical History
Morton I. Grossman (1919-1981) received an M.D. and a Ph.D. in physiology under Andrew Ivy at Northwestern University, after which he worked at the University of Illinois. During World War II he served at the U.S. Army Medical Nutritional Laboratory. In 1955 he joined the UCLA School of Medicine in physiology and medicine and the Wadsworth Veterans Administration Hospital in West Los Angeles as Chief of Gastroenterology. Grossman promoted a multidisciplinary approach to digestive disorders by creating the Center for Ulcer Research and Education (CURE) in 1974. He was author or co-author of more than 300 papers on gastroenterology and gastrointestinal physiology, and served as Editor (1960-1965) and later chair of the editorial board of "Gastroenterology", the offical publication of the Gastroenterological Association.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the professional papers of Gastroenterologist Morton I. Grossman.
- Biographies and obituaries, 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Publications list through 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Oral history interview by James D. Boyle for the Americal Gastroenterological Association, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Tributes in "Gastroenterology" (v.83, no.1), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Proceedings of International Cimetidine Symposium (Shanghai)" dedicated to Grossman, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- License, 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Appointments and positions, intramural, 1953-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Appointments and positions, extramural, 1956-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- American Gastroenterological Association, President, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- CURE (Center for Ulcer Research and Education) Foundation (Los Angeles, CA), 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Research, 1959-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lectures, speeches, and conferences, 1947-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1956-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Andrew C. Ivy tributes, 1968-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Tributes by Grossman to Sherman M. Mellinkoff, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Certificates, awards, diplomas, and honors, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs, 1952-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)